Guide to the Freedman Family Papers and Other Documents 1765–1968 (bulk, 1930–1950) MS 231
New-York Historical Society
Freedman family papers and other documents
1765–1968 (bulk, 1930–1950)
New-York Historical Society
Freedman (Family)
MS 231
1.668 Linear feet in 4 document boxes plus 2 oversize folders.
A small collection documenting members of the Freedman family, who lived during the 1940s at the Imperial Court Hotel on Manhattan's Upper West Side: Helen (Fox) Freedman, her son, William, a World War II fighter pilot, and her daughter, Nancy Ruth, who sang professionally under the stage name "Nancy Reed." The collection includes material from other residents of the Imperial Court during the 1930s–1950s: furniture dealer Samuel L. Kuklin, nurse and maid Margaret Matilda Tomlinson, and Broadway musical singer Virginia Vonne. Also present is an unrelated mixture of 18th–20th-century material, notably two large group photographs of attendees to the convention of the Verhovay Aid Society, a Hungarian national fraternal organization, at Passaic, New Jersey, in July 1914.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
This collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Asadorian, 2006.
Mr. Asadorian, onetime assistant curator of manuscripts at the New-York Historical Society and later archivist in the Long Island Division (now called the Archives) at Queens Public Library, has also spent considerable time as an amateur urban archaeologist and rescuer of discarded documents, which he attempts to place in appropriate institutional custody. His activities have been profiled on multiple occasions by the New York Times, for instance: Diana Jean Schemo, "Have Archives, Will Travel," Wednesday, September 16, 1992. The lack of relationship among some of the materials in the present collection suggests Mr. Asadorian assembled them from disparate sources.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in three series:
Series I.
Freedman family, onetime residents of Imperial Court Hotel (307 West 79th Street, Manhattan), 1912–1948, undated
Series II.
Other residents of Imperial Court Hotel (307 West 79th Street, Manhattan), 1917–1956, undated
Series III.
Unrelated documents, 1765–1968, undated
Historical note
Constructed in 1906–1907 as the Lasanno Court, the building at 307 West 79th Street on Manhattan's Upper West Side offered residents spacious six- to eight-room apartments. It attracted such tenants as the family of journalist A. J. Liebling and the violinist Jascha Heifetz. By the 1930s the Bi-Bro Realty Corporation purchased the building and renamed it the Imperial Court Hotel, converting its apartments to single room occupancy "studios" with semi-private baths and housekeeping services.
Scope and Contents
Series I and II of this collection focus on onetime residents of the Imperial Court Hotel, at 307 West 79th Street, on Manhattan's Upper West Side, during the 1930s, 1940s, and 1950s: Helen (Fox) Freedman, her son, William "Bud" Freedman, a fighter pilot during World War II, and her daughter, Nancy Ruth Freedman, who sang professionally under the stage name "Nancy Reed" with a number of musical groups, most notably the Skitch Henderson Orchestra. Other residents of the Imperial Court were wholesale furniture dealer Samuel L. Kuklin, nurse and maid Margaret Matilda Tomlinson, and singer Virginia Vonne, who appeared in at least two Broadway musicals during the late 1930s. See the biographical notes in the container list for additional information.
Series III is a mixture of 18th, 19th, and 20-century documents unrelated to those in Series I and II or to each other. They were likely assembled by the donor from disparate sources. See the Immediate Source of Acquisition note for details.
Address books.; Autograph book.; Bank statements.; Bills (financial); Business cards.; Checks (bank checks); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Ephemera.; First day covers.; Naturalization records.; Newspaper clippings.; Photographs.; Ration books.; Receipts (financial records); Report cards.; School yearbooks.; Sheet music.; Telephone directories.; Hungarian Americans.; Women singers -- United States.; Upper West Side (New York, N.Y.); Cropper, Roy, approximately 1896-1954.; Freedman, Helen (Fox), 1895–1969.; Freedman, Nancy Ruth, 1928– .; Freedman, William Marvin, 1923–2006.; Kuklin, Samuel L., 1887–1956.; Reed, Nancy.; Tomlinson, Margaret Matilda, 1888–1963?; Vonne, Virginia, approximately 1917–?; St. Ann's Church (Bronx, New York, N.Y.); Verhovay Fraternal Insurance Association.
- Series I. Freedman family, onetime residents of Imperial Court Hotel (307 West 79th Street, Manhattan), 1912–1948
  Biographical note
  Helen (Fox) Freedman (1895–1969), widow of Samuel Stanley Freedman (d. 1936) was the mother of William Marvin "Bud" Freedman (1923–2006) and Nancy Ruth Freedman (1928– ). William was a member of the Black Widow Night Fighter Squadron during World War II. Nancy sang professionally, most notably with the Skitch Henderson Orchestra, under the name "Nancy Reed." The family—which sometimes also used the shortened surname "Reed"—lived at various times in Miami Beach, Florida; Akron, Ohio; Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania; and New York City. Helen often accompanied Nancy as chaperone to the cities where she was performing. Documents in the collection indicate they were residents of the Imperial Court Hotel (307 West 79th Street) on Manhattan's Upper West Side during the 1940s.
  - Subseries I.A. Helen (Fox) Freedman (1895–1969), 1912–1948
    - Bills, correspondence, receipts, etc., 1943–1948 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Corn Exchange Bank Trust Company statements and canceled checks, 1945–1948 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
      Scope and Contents
      Statements and checks for July–August 1945 and September 1947 through January 1948.
    - Address book, [1946–1947?] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Photographs, 1912–1940s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
      Most of these photographs were found scattered throughout the collection. It is unclear if they all stem from the Freedman / Reed family (William "Bud" and Nancy are recognizable in some shots), or if they belong to other residents of 307 West 79th Street, Manhattan (see Series II).
  - Subseries I.B. William Marvin "Bud" Freedman (1923–2006), 1940–1947
    - Correspondence, clippings, college grades, 1940, 1943–1947 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Life in the Service" Record Book [blank], 1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries I.C. Nancy Ruth Freedman / Nancy Reed (1928– ), 1930–1948
    - Sheet music & manuscripts, 1930–1947 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
      • "Always in My Heart" (1942) [incomplete score]
      • "Cement Mixer (Put-ti Put-ti)," Slim Gaillard and Lee Ricks (1946)
      • "Come With Me My Honey (The Song of Calypso Joe)," Mack David, Joan Whitney, and Alex Kramer (1944)
      • "Crosstown," James Cavanaugh, John Redmond, and Nat Simon (1940)
      • "Don't Fence Me In," Cole Porter (1944)
      • "Hiking in the Rockies With You," Harry LeRoy Elliott and Ethel Marie Isaak (1933)
      • "I only have eyes for you" [mss. orchestration for Hal McIntyre Orchestra by Nancy Reed]
      • "I Walked In With my Eyes Wide Open," Harold Adamson and Jimmy McHugh (1944)
      • "In a Garden in Old Kalua," Mickey Kippel and Jack Aronson (1933)
      • "In My Arms," Frank Loesser and Ted Grouya (1943)
      • "Is It Any Wonder?," Chas J. Sinning (1936)
      • "Is You Is, Or Is You Ain't (Ma' Baby)," Billy Austin and Louis Jordan (1944)
      • "It Could Happen To You," Johnny Burke and Jimmy Van Heusen (1944)
      • "I'm in a Jam with Baby," Ted Koehler, Ray Heindorf, and M. K. Jerome (1944)
      • "It's Love, Love, Love!," Mack David, Joan Whitney, Alex Kramer (1943)
      • "It's Swell of You," Mack Gordon and Harry Revel (1937)
      • "A Kiss Goodnight" [mss. vocal part]
      • "Lookie Lookie Lookie, Here Comes Cookie," Mack Gordon (1935) [1st violins and bass parts]
      • "Lover! Are You There?," Jack Segal and Dick Miles (1944) [2 copies]
      • "Milkman, Keep Those Bottles Quiet," Don Raye and Gene De Paul (1944)
      • "The Music Goes 'Round and Around," "Red" Hodgson, Edward Farley, Michael Riley (1935)
      • "My Ideal," Leo Robin, Newell Chase, and Richard A. Whiting (1930)
      • "San Fernando Valley," Gordon Jenkins (1943)
      • "She Broke My Heart in Three Places," Milton Drake, Al Hoffman, Jerry Livingston (1944)
      • "Tomorrow is a Dream" (1947) [mss. by Nancy Reed & Buddy Freedman]
      • "Too Marvelous For Words" [two-part mss. arrangement for female and male voices]
      • "Without a Sweetheart," Henry Nemo (1944)
      • "Would'st Could I But Kiss Thy Hand, Oh Babe," Will Osborne and Dick Rogers (1940)
      • "You Don't Have to Know the Language," Johnny Burke and James Van Heusen (1947) [2 copies]
    - Bills, correspondence, ephemera, receipts, 1938–1948, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Diary, 1940 January 1-August 28 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
      "Nancy Ruth Freedman / 1400 Pennsylvania Ave. / Miami Beach / Florida / Ida M. Fisher Jr. Hi." With list of addresses.
    - Autograph book, 1940 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
      "This auto-graph book / belongs to / Nancy Freedman / 1400 Pennsylvania Ave. / Miami Beach, Florida / January 6, 1940." Signed by family, friends, and some celebrities, such as singer and actress Dixie Dunbar (1919–1991) and ventriloquist Edgar Bergen (1903–1978). With tipped in photographs and ephemera.
    - Yearbook, Miami Beach Senior High School (Miami Beach, Fla.), 1942 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
      1942 edition of the Typhoon, with many autographs to Nancy Freedman.
    - Report cards, Taylor Allderdice High School (Pittsburgh, Pa.), 1943–1944 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper, Taylor Allderdice High School (Pittsburgh, Pa.), 1943–1945 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
      Three issues of The Foreword:
      • vol. 33, no. 8 (December 23, 1943)
      • vol. 35, no. 3 (October 20, 1944)
      • vol. 36, no. 7 (May 18, 1945)
      Includes printed program of the Class of 1945's production of "Janie," a comedy in three acts, which is advertised in the May 18, 1945 issue of The Foreword. Nancy Freedman performed the title role.
    - Newspaper & periodical clippings, 1943–1948, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
    - Yearbook, Taylor Allderdice High School (Pittsburgh, Pa.), 1944 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
      With many autographs to Nancy Freedman, and tipped in photographs, notes, and ephemera.
    - Classmate photographs (5), Taylor Allderdice High School (Pittsburgh, Pa.), 1945 February-March (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
      Each inscribed to Nancy Freedman.
    - Diploma and commencement ephemera, Taylor Allderdice High School (Pittsburgh, Pa.), 1945 June (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
      Contains program for "Thirty-First Commencement, Taylor Allderdice High School, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania) (June 13-14, 1945), admission ticket (June 14, 1945), and Nancy Freedman's diploma (June 22, 1945).
    - Julliard School of Music Summer School, 1945 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
      Includes course catalog, Nancy Freedman's class schedule and muisc theory exercise book.
    - Trade publications, 1945, 1947 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
      • Song Parade, vol. 4, no. 5 (April 1945)
      • Hit Parader, vol. 3, no. 11 (September 1945)
      • International Musician, vol. 46, no. 4 (October 1947)
    - Dorothy Shay photographs (2), [1948] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
      Two photographs of American comedic recording artist Dorothy Shay (1921–1978), inscribed to Nancy. Shay appeared on the same bill with Nancy Reed (singing with the Skitch Henderson Orchestra) in the Boulevard Room, Stevens Hotel, Chicago. See the clipping from Variety, January 14, 1948, in Box 2, Folder 7.
    - "Pryde and Day" photograph, [1948] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
      Photograph of juggling team Pryde and Day inscribed to Helen and Nancy. They appeared on the same bill with Nancy Reed (singing with the Skitch Henderson Orchestra) in the Boulevard Room, Stevens Hotel, Chicago. See the clipping from Variety, January 14, 1948, in Box 2, Folder 7.
    - Nancy Reed publicity photographs, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
- Series II. Other residents of Imperial Court Hotel (307 West 79th Street, Manhattan)
  Samuel Kuklin, Margaret Tomlinson, and Virginia Vonne were residents of the Imperial Court Hotel (307 West 79th Street), on Manhattan's Upper West Side, during the 1930s, 1940s, and 1950s.
  Samuel L. Kuklin (1887–1956) was a wholesale dealer of furniture, whose many contacts in the trade are reflected in the business cards in Box 3, Folder 8.
  Margaret Matilda Tomlinson (1888–1963?) was a Canadian-born, naturalized U.S. citizen who worked as a maid and nurse in New York City. A portion of her correspondence in Box 3, Folder 9 deals with her attempts to secure personal health care.
  Virginia Vonne (born in Missouri about 1917) was a singer known to have performed in at least two Broadway musicals: "Hooray For What!" at the Winter Garden Theatre (December 1, 1937–May 21, 1938) and "Blossom Time" at the 46th Street Theatre (December 26, 1938–January 7, 1939).
  - Subseries II.A. Samuel L. Kuklin (1887–1956), 1939–1941
    - Bills, correspondence, receipts, etc., 1939–1941 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
    - Business cards, [circa 1940?] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
  - Subseries II.B. Margaret Matilda Tomlinson (1888–1963?), 1917–1956, undated
    - Correspondence, ephemera, etc., 1917–1956, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
    - Certificate of citizenship, 1939 September 21 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    - Ration books, 1942 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
  - Subseries II.C. Virginia Vonne (circa 1917–?), 1938–1940
    - "Firefly", 1938 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
      Two newspapers reviews (July 12, 1938) of the Rudolph Friml operetta "Firefly," in which Vonne performed at Jones Beach, Long Island. With cover letter from a Dr. Robert M. Colbert.
    - "Blossom Time", 1938–1939 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
      Material from Vonne's involvement with this Broadway musical, which ran for 19 performances on Broadway at the 46th Street Theatre, December 26, 1938-January 7, 1939. Includes her contract with the Select Operating Company; vocal scores ("Chorus" and "Three Waltzes Chorus"); dialogue part of "Greta"; printed program for previews at the Nixon Theatre, Pittsburgh, beginning October 10, 1938 (the program lists her name as both "Vonne" and "Vahn" and her character as "Rosi" instead of "Rose"); a review by Dick Fortune from The Pittsburgh Press (October 11, 1938); and a signed photographic portrait inscribed "To dainty Virginia" from Mary McCoy, who played "Mitzi" in the show.
    - Correspondence, ephemera, etc., 1939 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
      Includes Vonne's New York State Department of Labor Unemployment Insurance Identification Card; her contract with Operatic Festival Inc., a stock company at Louisville, Kentucky; and correspondence and brochures from the Insulite Company of Minneapolis, manufacturers of wall and ceiling materials.
    - Letters from Roy Cropper aboard the R.M.S. Nieuw Amsterdam, 1940 January-March (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
      Roy Cropper (1894–1954), a tenor, was performing in the "Seabreeze Revue" aboard the R.M.S. Nieuw Amsterdam, a cruise ship of the Holland-America Line, when he wrote to Vonne. A year prior the two appeared in the same Broadway production of "Blossom Time," at the 46th Street Theatre (December 26, 1938-January 7, 1939). Cropper played "Baron Franz Schober." Vonne played "Rose." This folder includes an invitation to a dinner and musicale in honor of Giovanni Martinelli, sponsor of the New York Light Opera Guild, January 21, 1940, at which Roy Cropper sang the role of Orlando in Florence Wickham's "Rosalind." With newspaper clippings announcing the performance as well as one giving details of the Nieuw Amsterdam's West Indies cruise.
- Series III. Unrelated documents, 1765–1968, undated
  The items in this series are unrelated to those in Series I and II, and are unrelated, for the most part, to each other. They include a mix of 18th, 19th, and 20th-century documents in a variety of formats: contracts, deeds, ephemera, photographs, and a few objects. Of chief interest are the two large, mounted photographs of attendees to the convention of the Verhovay Aid Society, a Hungarian national fraternal organization, at Passaic, New Jersey, in July 1914.
  - Abstract from a [land] patent..., 1765 June 6 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
    "Abstract from a Patent Dated the 6th day of June 1765 and granted to John Montressor, Francis Mee and Robert Wallace" for "All that certain Tract or parcel of Land situate lying and being in the County of Albany on the west side of Lake Champlain within Our province of New York as also four small Islands called Les Isles des quatres Vents lying in the said Lake... ."
  - Contract to establish smelting works, 1775 July 25 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
    "In consequence of our being about to establish Works in this or any other Colony of North America for the smelting, refining, and manufacturing of Ores produced from Mines belonging in partnership to John Sebastian Stephanÿ, John Kohl, and Gosninus Erkelens, all of the City, County, and Province of New York... ."
  - Gates's Troy Almanac, for the Year of Our Lord 1837 (Troy, N.Y.: Elias Gates), [1836] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
  - St. Ann's Church, Morrisania [The Bronx]. Deed and assignment, 1854, 1855 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
    • St. Ann's Church, Morrisania. Deed, to The Corporation of St. Paul's Church, Morrisania, January 2, 1854.
    • St. Ann's Church, Morrisania. Assignment of mortgage to Edward Haight, September 20, 1855.
  - Levi R. Leeds letter to Captain Jacob Johnson, 1861 May 16 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
    Levi R. Leeds, a patient in Brooklyn City Hospital suffering from "that awful scourge consumption," writes to Captain Jacob Johnson, who was possibly his brother-in-law, husband of "Sister Jane" [Margaret Jane (Leeds) Johnson?].
  - The Troy Daily Whig [newspaper], Troy, N.Y., 1861 November 14 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
  - Verhovay Aid Society photographs (2), 1914 July (Oversize (small), Folder 1 of 2)
    Two large mounted photographs (mounts measure 22 x 14 inches) of attendees to the convention of the Verhovay Aid Society, a Hungarian national fraternal organization, Passaic, New Jersey, July 1914. The second of the two listed below shows the group at flag raising ceremonies on Long Island on Sunday, July 26, 1914 (see Passaic Daily News, Monday, July 27, 1914, p. 13).
    • A VERHOVAY KONVENCIO DELEGATUSAI PASSAICON 1914 JULIUS HÒ-BAN BELDEGREEN FENYKEPE 52 32 AVE C N.Y. {Delegates to the Averhovay Convention, Passaic, July 1914; photographed by Beldegreen Fenykepe, 32 Avenue C, N.Y.}
    • A VERHOVAY EGYLET 38 IK N.Y. FIOKJANAK ZAZLOSZENTELSI UNNE PELYE 1914 JULIUS 2GAN [26AN?] {The Averhovay Association, Branch No. 38 of New York}
  - Palmström von Christian Morgenstern [German poetry], 1920 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
  - First Day Covers [postal history] (19), 1937–1968 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
    Postage stamps and cancelations commemorating
    • Hawaii (1937)
    • Coronado Cuarto Centennial (1940)
    • National Defense (1940)
    • Vermont 150th Anniversary of Statehood (1941)
    • Fort Deven's Airport, Ayer, Mass. (1941)
    • 50th Anniversary of Motion Pictures (1944)
    • Greater New York Golden Jubilee (1948)
    • Rough Riders (1948)
    • Forks of Salmon, California (1948)
    • Centennial of the American Poultry Industry (1948)
    • Daffodil Festival, Tacoma, Washington (1948)
    • OHPEX '49 (1949)
    • Marshall Pass, Colorado (1949)
    • 175th Anniversary arrival of Marquis de LaFayette (1952)
    • James Monroe (1954)
    • Children of All Nations (1956)
    • Flushing Remonstrance (1957)
    • Henry Ford (1968)
    • Leif Ericson (1968)
  - Staten Island telephone directory, 1941 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
  - Jokes / ancecdotes, [1952] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
    Jokes and humorous ancedotes typed on 33 strips of paper, one of which is dated October 10, 1952.
  - [Christening bonnet?], undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)
  - Loose ephemera (5 folders), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13-17)
    Includes greeting cards, pre-printed return mailing envelopes, brochures for Morningside Country Club (Greenwood Lake, N.Y.), Bantam automobile advertisements, etc.
  - Manuscript English-German dictionary / phrase book, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 18)
  - [Purse?], undated (Oversize (small), Folder 2 of 2)
  - Wallet, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19)
    Holds a card with the word "REPUBLICAN" typed above the numbers "0987654321" followed by the same written in reverse: "NACILBUPER" above "1234567890."